<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/vim-web/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/vim-web/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-16T19:44:28+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/feed.xml</id><title type="html">visualization and image data management</title><subtitle>VIM (Visualization and Image Data Management) aims to connect research labs, university hospitals, and open source partners. Its mission is to provide a platform for research and educational exchange and to join efforts in developing and standardizing data formats, platforms and interfaces for analyzing and communicating biomedical imaging data.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Meeting 23</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/12/08/meeting-23.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Meeting 23" /><published>2023-12-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/12/08/meeting-23</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/12/08/meeting-23.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">21th Meeting “Towards a thick-tissue 3D atlas for characterizing cell neighborhoods and shape in melanoma with CyCIF”</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/11/17/meeting-22.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="21th Meeting “Towards a thick-tissue 3D atlas for characterizing cell neighborhoods and shape in melanoma with CyCIF”" /><published>2023-11-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/11/17/meeting-22</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/11/17/meeting-22.html"><![CDATA[<p>Please join us Friday, 11/17/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “Towards a thick-tissue 3D atlas for characterizing cell neighborhoods and shape in melanoma with CyCIF”. Microscopy-based tissue imaging is commonly performed at a resolution sufficient to determine cell types but not detect the subtle morphological features associated with cytoskeletal reorganisation, juxtracrine signalling, or membrane trafficking. Here we introduce a 3D imaging approach with high-resolution 54-plex cyclic immunofluorescence (CyCIF) using existing instruments and reagents that is able to characterize a wide variety of organelles and structures at sub-micron scale, cell morphology at the cellular level, while simultaneously quantifying millimetre-scale spatial features.</p>

<p>Presenters: Clarence is the Director of Microscopy and Image Analysis at the Laboratory of Systems Pharmacology (LSP) under Professor Peter Sorger, as well as a research associate at the Image and Data Analysis Core (IDAC) under Dr. Hunter Elliott, and regularly works with the Nikon Imaging Center (NIC) under Dr. Jennifer Waters at Harvard Medical School (HMS). His main interests are in aiding experimental design of imaging assays through collaboration, as well as applying deep learning to 2D, 3D and 4D image analysis problems.</p>]]></content><author><name>Clarence Yapp, Microscopy and Image Analysis at the LSP. Harvard Medical School</name></author><category term="imaging," /><category term="management," /><category term="tools," /><category term="visualization" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please join us Friday, 11/17/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “Towards a thick-tissue 3D atlas for characterizing cell neighborhoods and shape in melanoma with CyCIF”. Microscopy-based tissue imaging is commonly performed at a resolution sufficient to determine cell types but not detect the subtle morphological features associated with cytoskeletal reorganisation, juxtracrine signalling, or membrane trafficking. Here we introduce a 3D imaging approach with high-resolution 54-plex cyclic immunofluorescence (CyCIF) using existing instruments and reagents that is able to characterize a wide variety of organelles and structures at sub-micron scale, cell morphology at the cellular level, while simultaneously quantifying millimetre-scale spatial features.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">21th Meeting “SpatialData - an open and universal data framework for spatial omics”</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/10/13/meeting-21.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="21th Meeting “SpatialData - an open and universal data framework for spatial omics”" /><published>2023-10-13T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/10/13/meeting-21</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/10/13/meeting-21.html"><![CDATA[<p>Please join us Friday, 10/13/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “SpatialData: an open and universal data framework for spatial omics”. Spatially resolved omics technologies are transforming our understanding of biological tissues. However, handling uni- and multi-modal spatial omics datasets remains a challenge owing to large volumes of data, heterogeneous data types and the lack of unified spatially-aware data structures. Here, we introduce SpatialData, a framework that establishes a unified and extensible multi-platform file-format, lazy representation of larger-than-memory data, transformations, and alignment to common coordinate systems. SpatialData facilitates spatial annotations and cross-modal aggregation and analysis, the utility of which is illustrated via multiple vignettes, including integrative analysis on a multi-modal Xenium and Visium breast cancer study.</p>

<p>Presenters: Giovanni Palla is currently a PhD candidate at Helmholtz Munich advised by Professor Fabian Theis. He received his Bachelors degree in biotechnology from the University of Trento in 2016, and Masters degree in drug innovation from Utrecht University in 2018. In addition to his research on algorithms for analysis of atlas-scale and spatially-resolved single-cell data, Giovanni is also a co-founder and developer in the Scverse project to develop foundational open-source tools for single-cell omics data analysis.</p>

<p>Preprint: https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2023.05.05.539647v1.full</p>]]></content><author><name>Giovanni Palla (Institute of Computational Biology, Helmholtz and TUM School of Life Sciences Weihenstephan, Munich, Germany)</name></author><category term="formats," /><category term="tools," /><category term="management" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please join us Friday, 10/13/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “SpatialData: an open and universal data framework for spatial omics”. Spatially resolved omics technologies are transforming our understanding of biological tissues. However, handling uni- and multi-modal spatial omics datasets remains a challenge owing to large volumes of data, heterogeneous data types and the lack of unified spatially-aware data structures. Here, we introduce SpatialData, a framework that establishes a unified and extensible multi-platform file-format, lazy representation of larger-than-memory data, transformations, and alignment to common coordinate systems. SpatialData facilitates spatial annotations and cross-modal aggregation and analysis, the utility of which is illustrated via multiple vignettes, including integrative analysis on a multi-modal Xenium and Visium breast cancer study.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">20th Meeting “The Imaging Data Commons as a platform for reproducible reasearch in digital pathology”</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/09/15/meeting-20.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="20th Meeting “The Imaging Data Commons as a platform for reproducible reasearch in digital pathology”" /><published>2023-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/09/15/meeting-20</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/09/15/meeting-20.html"><![CDATA[<p>Please join us Friday, 09/15/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “The Imaging Data Commons as a platform for reproducible reasearch in digital pathology”. When developing machine learning (ML)-based solutions in computational pathology one of the often underestimated but major challenges is to ensure their reproducibilty. The National Cancer Institute (NCI) Imaging Data Commons (IDC) is a new cloud-based repository within the US national Cancer Research Data Commons (CRDC), which provides more than 120 cancer image collections according to the FAIR principles and is designed to be used with cloud ML services. In our work, we investigated how the IDC and cloud ML services can be used in combination to facilitate reproducibility in computational pathology research. For this purpose we developed a use case, in which we trained and applied a tissue classification model to distinguish between healthy tissue and two different tumor subtypes. We used different datasets from the IDC and implemented our experiments using Google Colaboratory and Google Vertex AI Notebooks.
This talk will be about our experiences with setting up a reproducible computational pathology pipeline and summarize some of our pitfalls and learnings.</p>

<p>Presenters: Daniela Schacherer, M.Sc.: Daniela Schacherer has a background in Molecular Biotechnology and Computer Science and is working as an Image Analysis researcher with Fraunhofer MEVIS in Bremen (Germany) since May 2020. She is part of the IDC team since July 2020 and in the project focusses on the work with digital pathology images. André Homeyer, PhD: André Homeyer is a senior scientist in computational pathology at Fraunhofer MEVIS in Bremen, Germany. He has been working in this field for more than 10 years and is the IDC project lead on Fraunhofer MEVIS side since the start of the project in 2019.</p>]]></content><author><name>Daniela Schacherer, André Homeyer (Fraunhofer MEVIS, Bremen, Germany)</name></author><category term="platforms," /><category term="tools," /><category term="formats," /><category term="visualization" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please join us Friday, 09/15/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “The Imaging Data Commons as a platform for reproducible reasearch in digital pathology”. When developing machine learning (ML)-based solutions in computational pathology one of the often underestimated but major challenges is to ensure their reproducibilty. The National Cancer Institute (NCI) Imaging Data Commons (IDC) is a new cloud-based repository within the US national Cancer Research Data Commons (CRDC), which provides more than 120 cancer image collections according to the FAIR principles and is designed to be used with cloud ML services. In our work, we investigated how the IDC and cloud ML services can be used in combination to facilitate reproducibility in computational pathology research. For this purpose we developed a use case, in which we trained and applied a tissue classification model to distinguish between healthy tissue and two different tumor subtypes. We used different datasets from the IDC and implemented our experiments using Google Colaboratory and Google Vertex AI Notebooks. This talk will be about our experiences with setting up a reproducible computational pathology pipeline and summarize some of our pitfalls and learnings.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">19th Meeting “VR, data storytelling, AI - more than a fad for visual analytics of hi-plex imaging data?”</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/07/14/meeting-19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="19th Meeting “VR, data storytelling, AI - more than a fad for visual analytics of hi-plex imaging data?”" /><published>2023-07-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/07/14/meeting-19</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/07/14/meeting-19.html"><![CDATA[<p>Please join us Friday, 07/14/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “VR, data storytelling, AI: more than a fad for visual analytics of hi-plex imaging data?”. Can virtual reality (VR) and data storytelling enrich visual analytics of highly multiplex microscopic imaging data? With NCI SBIR funding aimed at supporting NCI atlas building projects such as HTAN and HubMAP, Quantitative Imaging Systems, Flow Immersive, and OHSU piloted extensions to our QiTissue multiplex visual analytics and Flow’s XR, data storytelling, and AI platforms to explore.</p>

<p>Presenters: Damir Sudar, CSO of Quantitative Imaging Systems LLC, https://qitissue.com/, Jason Marsh, CEO of Flow Immersive, Inc., https://flowimmersive.com/</p>

<p><img src="https://github.com/vis-image-management/vim-web/assets/31503434/4819ad91-e283-48d2-997d-729ebd1d0ff5" alt="image" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Damir Sudar (OHSU &amp; CSO of Quantitative Imaging Systems LLC), Jason Marsh (CEO of Flow Immersive Inc.)</name></author><category term="visual-analytics," /><category term="tools," /><category term="viewers," /><category term="visualization" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please join us Friday, 07/14/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “VR, data storytelling, AI: more than a fad for visual analytics of hi-plex imaging data?”. Can virtual reality (VR) and data storytelling enrich visual analytics of highly multiplex microscopic imaging data? With NCI SBIR funding aimed at supporting NCI atlas building projects such as HTAN and HubMAP, Quantitative Imaging Systems, Flow Immersive, and OHSU piloted extensions to our QiTissue multiplex visual analytics and Flow’s XR, data storytelling, and AI platforms to explore.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">18th Meeting “Computational Segmentation and Visualization of Multiplex Segmentation Data”</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/06/16/meeting-18.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="18th Meeting “Computational Segmentation and Visualization of Multiplex Segmentation Data”" /><published>2023-06-16T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/06/16/meeting-18</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/06/16/meeting-18.html"><![CDATA[<p>Please join us Friday, 06/16/2023 11AM ET for two talk titled “Computational Segmentation of Renal Microanatomy, and Implication in Diabetes and Transplant
“ and “Interactive Visualization of Kidney Structural Segmentations and Associated Pathomic Features on Whole Slide Images”. In this talk, we will introduce computational renal pathology, and discuss detection, segmentation, quantification, and classification of microanatomical structures from renal histology giga-pixel size whole slide images. We will also discuss our ongoing efforts on computational data fusion integrating imaging morphometric and molecular omics data. We will conclude by discussing potential implications of our tools in the area of diabetes and renal transplantation.</p>]]></content><author><name>Pinaki Sarder, Ph.D. (University of Florida, Mark Keller (Harvard Medical School)</name></author><category term="tools," /><category term="visualization," /><category term="platforms," /><category term="formats" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please join us Friday, 06/16/2023 11AM ET for two talk titled “Computational Segmentation of Renal Microanatomy, and Implication in Diabetes and Transplant “ and “Interactive Visualization of Kidney Structural Segmentations and Associated Pathomic Features on Whole Slide Images”. In this talk, we will introduce computational renal pathology, and discuss detection, segmentation, quantification, and classification of microanatomical structures from renal histology giga-pixel size whole slide images. We will also discuss our ongoing efforts on computational data fusion integrating imaging morphometric and molecular omics data. We will conclude by discussing potential implications of our tools in the area of diabetes and renal transplantation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">17th Meeting “WebAtlas Pipeline for Integrated Single Cell and Spatial Transcriptomic Data”</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/05/19/meeting-17.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="17th Meeting “WebAtlas Pipeline for Integrated Single Cell and Spatial Transcriptomic Data”" /><published>2023-05-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/05/19/meeting-17</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/05/19/meeting-17.html"><![CDATA[<p>Please join us Friday, 05/19/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “WebAtlas pipeline for integrated single cell and spatial transcriptomic data”. Single cell and spatial transcriptomics illuminate complementary features of tissues. However, online dissemination and exploration of integrated datasets is challenging due to the heterogeneity and scale of data. We introduce the WebAtlas pipeline for user-friendly sharing and interactive navigation of integrated datasets. WebAtlas unifies commonly used atlassing technologies into the cloud-optimised Zarr format and builds on Vitessce to enable remote data navigation. We showcase WebAtlas on the developing human lower limb to cross-query cell types and genes across single cell, sequencing- and imaging-based spatial transcriptomic data.</p>]]></content><author><name>Omer Bayraktar, Tong Li, David Horsfall (Wellcome Sanger Institute, Newcastle University)</name></author><category term="tools," /><category term="viewers," /><category term="platforms," /><category term="formats," /><category term="management" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please join us Friday, 05/19/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “WebAtlas pipeline for integrated single cell and spatial transcriptomic data”. Single cell and spatial transcriptomics illuminate complementary features of tissues. However, online dissemination and exploration of integrated datasets is challenging due to the heterogeneity and scale of data. We introduce the WebAtlas pipeline for user-friendly sharing and interactive navigation of integrated datasets. WebAtlas unifies commonly used atlassing technologies into the cloud-optimised Zarr format and builds on Vitessce to enable remote data navigation. We showcase WebAtlas on the developing human lower limb to cross-query cell types and genes across single cell, sequencing- and imaging-based spatial transcriptomic data.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">16th Meeting “Education and Training for Visualization Tools”</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/04/21/meeting-16.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="16th Meeting “Education and Training for Visualization Tools”" /><published>2023-04-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/04/21/meeting-16</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/04/21/meeting-16.html"><![CDATA[<p>Please join us Friday, 04/21/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “Education and Training for Visualization Tools” followed by a discussion on considerations for writing effective software documentation and what community resources would be helpful.</p>]]></content><author><name>Han Xu</name></author><category term="standards," /><category term="training," /><category term="education," /><category term="tools," /><category term="management" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please join us Friday, 04/21/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “Education and Training for Visualization Tools” followed by a discussion on considerations for writing effective software documentation and what community resources would be helpful.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">15th Meeting “Scrollytelling in Medical Communication”</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/03/10/meeting-15.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="15th Meeting “Scrollytelling in Medical Communication”" /><published>2023-03-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/03/10/meeting-15</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/03/10/meeting-15.html"><![CDATA[<p>Please join us Friday, 03/10/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “Scrollytelling in medical communication”.</p>

<p>About the Speaker: Eric Moerth conducted his PhD in Medical Visualization at the University of Bergen where he mainly focused on helping radiologists in analysing multimodal medical imaging data.</p>]]></content><author><name>Eric Moerth</name></author><category term="visual-analytics," /><category term="viewers," /><category term="platforms," /><category term="visualization" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please join us Friday, 03/10/2023 11AM ET for a talk titled “Scrollytelling in medical communication”.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">14th Meeting “Report on Status and Roadmap Concerns for OME-NGFF”</title><link href="/vim-web/2023/02/10/meeting-14.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="14th Meeting “Report on Status and Roadmap Concerns for OME-NGFF”" /><published>2023-02-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-16T19:43:46+00:00</updated><id>/vim-web/2023/02/10/meeting-14</id><content type="html" xml:base="/vim-web/2023/02/10/meeting-14.html"><![CDATA[<p>Please join us Friday, 02/10/2023 11AM ET for a talk about the imaging format OME-NGFF with the title “Report on Status and Roadmap Concerns for OME-NGFF”</p>]]></content><author><name>Erin Diel and Josh Moore</name></author><category term="visual-analytics," /><category term="viewers," /><category term="platforms," /><category term="visualization" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Please join us Friday, 02/10/2023 11AM ET for a talk about the imaging format OME-NGFF with the title “Report on Status and Roadmap Concerns for OME-NGFF”]]></summary></entry></feed>